Guide to the Edmund Gosse Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Edmund Gosse collection
1876-1927
GEN MSS 14
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.2
(1 box)
Contains letters from Gosse to various people, including Grant Allen and Clinton Scollard. There is also a menu of a breakfast given for Gosse, signed by the attendees, and a holograph version of Gosse's poem, "Yew-Berries."
Gosse, Edmund, 1849-1928
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Type of accesion (gift or purchase) and date of acquisition is noted in the box-and-folder listing. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to Edmund Grosse, which the library has chosen to group and list as an artificial collection.
Allen, Grant, 1848-1899; Gosse, Edmund, 1849-1928; Scollard, Clinton, 1860-1932
- I. Letters from Edmund Gosse, 1887-98
  - 6 ALS to Grant Allen, [London], 1887-98 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Gift, 1951.
  - 2 ALS to Mrs. Grant Allen [Ellen Jerrard Allen], [London], 1884, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - ALS to Sir Frederic Burton, London, 1881 Feb 10 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Purchase, 1957.
  - ALS to [Archibald Young Cambell] [London], [19]17 May 24 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Purchase, 1969.
  - ALS to [Edward] Clodd, [London], [1917?] Jul (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - ALS to Albert S. Cook, [London], 1909 Jan 28 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Removed from Cook's A Concordance to the English Poems of Thomas Gray (Boston, 1908). Gift, 1956.
  - ALS to Mr. Crawfurd, [London], 1902 Sep 15 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Gift, 1959.
  - ANS to Earl E. Fisk, [London], [19]21 Aug 12 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Removed from: Books on the Table... by Edmund Gosse (New York, 1921). Purchase, 1960.
  - ANS to C. B. Foote, 1895 Mar 20 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Removed from: In Russet and Silver by Edmund Gosse (London, 1894). Purchase, 1991.
  - ALS to [Henry?] Wilson-Fox, [London], 1904 Jan 21 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Concerning affairs of the Board of Trade. Gift, 1957.
  - ALS to [Robert Watson?] Frazer, London, 1894 Sep 10 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Purchase, 1954.
  - ALS to Richard Watson Gilder, London, 1892 Jan 2 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Gosse says that both he and Henry James are writing biographical articles on Wolcott Balestier. Purchase, 1954.
  - AL to [Sir John Hammerton], London, 1903 Feb 11 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Grants permission to Hammerton to republish some of Gosse's articles on R. L. Stevenson. Gift, 1957.
  - ALS to Cuthbert Morley Headlam, London (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Gift, 1957.
  - ALS to Mr. Hipkins, [London], 1876 Jan 7 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Gift, 1960.
  - ALS to [W. Somerset Maugham], 17, Hanover Terrace, Regent's Park, N. W., [London], [19]16 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Purchase, 1997.
  - 2 ALS to Mr. [Clinton] Scollard, Board of Trade, S. W., [London], 1886, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Gift, 1946.
  - ANS to Logan Pearsall Smith, [London], [19]17 Mar 13 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Gift, 1982.
  - ALS to Charles A. Stonehill, Savoy Hotel, West Cliff, Bournemouth, 1927 Sep 13 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Gift, 1944.
  - 2 ALS to Algernon Charles Swinburne, 1879, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Gift, 1971.
  - ALS to the Reverend, the Master of Trinity, D.D. [William Hepworth Thompson], [Trinity College], 1885 Mar 9 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - ALS to [Sir William] Watson, [London], [18]95 Nov 18 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Purchase, 1982.
  - ALS to unidentified correspondant, Mountstewart, Ireland, 1914 Apr 11 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- II. Other, 1885 Jan 26
  - Menu Card for Breakfast of Edmund Gosse, [New York], 1885 Jan 26 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    With 23 autograph signatures. Purchase, 1960.
  - "Yew-Berries," poem, manuscript, signed, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
    With typed transcript. Purchase, 1995.